In this class our project is going
En este curso nuestro proyecto va a ser
to be to build a blog using MongoDB and Python.
construir un blog usando MongoDB y Python.
And to do that we're going to need a web
Para hacer eso vamos a necesitar un framework
framework because this is going to be a web application.
web, ya que vamos a hacer una aplicación web.
And the one we're going to use in the class is called Bottle.
El framework que vamos a usar durante el curso se llama Bottle.
Bottle is a very simple web framework that is minimalistic,
Bottle es un framework web minimalista muy simple,
it has basic templates, and lets you create web pages.
tiene plantillas básicas y permite crear páginas web.
It's probably not something you'd use for a production
Probablemente no sea algo que usarías para un proyecto
project, but you could.
en producción, pero podrías.
But it's very good for this class
En cualquier caso está muy bien para este curso
because it sort of strips out all the complexity of a lot
porque en cierto modo elimina toda la complejidad de
of the modern web programming.
la programación web moderna.
So let's go find and install it.
Vamos a localizarlo y a instalarlo.
It's a Python module.
Es un módulo de Python.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going
Lo que voy a hacer aquí es ir
to go to Google as I always do.
a Google, como siempre.
I'm a loyal Google user.
Soy un fiel usuario de Google.
And I'm going to say Bottle Python framework.
Y voy a poner "bottle python framework".
And it looks like it's a Bottle.py.org.
Y parece que existe un "bottlepy.org".
And so I click on it, and I notice
Hago click en el enlace y veo que
this is the preview release, and I want the stable release.
existe una versión "preview", pero quiero la versión estable.
So I click there.
Así que hago click ahí.
And now it gives me some basic information about this module.
Y ahora me da cierta información básica sobre este módulo.
And you can see they actually have an example Hello World
Y puedes ver que tienen un programa "Hello World"
program.
de ejemplo.
And we're going to run that program.
Vamos a ejecutar ese programa.
It's a very short program.
Es un programa muy corto.
I'm going to take you through it, line by line,
Voy a guiarte por el programa línea a línea,
and show you what it does.
y te enseñaré qué hace.
But right now we want to download it and install it.
Pero ahora queremos descargarlo e instalarlo.
Now they suggest that we get it from the PyPi repository,
Ahora nos sugieren que lo obtengamos del repositorio PyPI,
and they suggest that we use easy_install.
y que usemos easy_install.
I prefer to use PIP.
Yo prefiero usar pip.
We have PIP installed in both the MAC and the Windows
Hemos instalado pip tanto en Mac como en Windows,
PC that we showed in the earlier lesson.
como vimos en las lecciones anteriores.
So let's go ahead and use PIP to do this.
Así que seguiremos adelante y usaremos pip.
So I'm going get a Command window.
Voy a abrir una ventana de comandos.
I'm going to become root, which I need to do on this Mac.
Cambio al usuario "root", es necesario hacerlo en Mac,
But I shouldn't need to do it on the Windows box, I don't think.
pero no debería necesitar hacerlo en una máquina Windows, creo.
So pip install bottle.
"pip install bottle".
All right.
Bien.
So that installed the 12.8 version,
Se instaló la versión 0.12.8,
which is good news because we know that the version
lo cual es una buena noticia porque sabemos que la versión
number 13 was unstable.
0.13 es inestable,
And so we don't want that one.
y por tanto no queremos usarla.
Let's see if that's true.
Veamos si es cierto.
It said the dot 12 was stable, and this is dot 12.
Decía que la versión 0.12 era estable, y ésta es la 0.12.
So that's good.
Así que está bien.
That's the stable version.
Es la versión estable.
And now we need that little program.
Y ahora necesitamos ese programita.
So to do that, the easiest thing to do
Para hacer eso, lo más sencillo es simplemente
is just to copy it with your mouse.
copiarlo con el ratón.
And I've already done that.
Y ya he hecho eso.
You can use whatever editor you want.
Puedes usar el editor que prefieras.
I'm going to use Emacs because that's
Yo voy a usar Emacs porque me
what I'm most familiar with, and I'm just
resulta muy familar, y ahora voy a
going to take you through this program, line by line,
guiarte por este programa, línea a línea,
and show you what it does.
mostrándote qué hace.
So from Bottle it imports a few different methods-- route, run,
Importa unos cuantos métodos diferentes de Bottle: "route", "run"
and template.
y "template".
It uses these decorators, and these decorators
Usa estos decoradores, que
are used to set up URLs that the web
se utilizan para configurar las URLs que atenderá
server is going to listen on.
el servidor web.
So here it's saying that it wants
Entonces, aquí está diciendo que quiere
to listen on slash hello slash name,
capturar "/hello/",
that that's a URL this program will handle,
es una URL que manejará este programa,
where name is a variable.
donde "name" es una variable.
So it could be hello slash Andrew or hello slash Bob.
Podría ser "/hello/Andrew" o "/hello/Bob",
And that it will return this template, which
y devolverá esta plantilla, que
is right in place.
está aquí mismo.
And you can also get it from a templates directory,
También puedes recuperarla de un directorio de plantillas,
but in this case it's inline to template.
pero en este caso es una plantilla en línea.
It says return hello name.
Dice: devuelve "Hello }!".
It's bolded with an exclamation mark,
Está en negrita y con un signo de exclamación,
and that's it, where name equals name.
y eso es todo, donde "name = name".
And the last thing is just telling
Y por último, le está diciendo
it to run the web server and listen on it.
que ejecute el servidor web y que escuche:
And so it says run host equals local host port 8080.
"run(host='localhost', port=8080)".
So let's run that and see what happens.
Ejecutemos el programa y veamos qué pasa.
So we're going to invoke the Python interpreter
Vamos a invocar el intérprete de Python
on hello Bottle.
sobre "hello_bottle.py".
This is not using MongoDB at all.
Esto no está usando MongoDB para nada.
All right.
Bien.
It's listening on port 8080.
Está escuchando en el puerto 8080.
Let's go back to the web browser.
Volvamos al navegador web.
Go to port 8080, the URL hello, and then append
Ve al puerto 8080, escribe la URL "/hello/", y a continuación añade
Andrew on the end and see if it says hello to me.
"Andrew" al final, veamos si me saluda.
It says hello Andrew.
Dice: "Hello Andrew!".
And we could also have it say, hello Eliot .
Y podríamos haber hecho que dijera "Hello Eliot!".
Hello Eliot.
"Hello Eliot!".
And it can say hello Richard, if we want.
Y si queremos, puede decir "Hello Richard!".
That's it.
Eso es.
And then you can see every time I hit the web server,
Puedes ver que cada vez que pongo algo en el navegador web
it prints out the URL that got hit, which
imprime lo que puse en la URL,
is Andrew, Eliot, and Richard.
"Andrew", "Eliot", and "Richard".
So that's how you install Bottle and how
Así es como se instala y ejecuta
you get it running on a Mac.
Bottle en un Mac.
And on Windows it's very similar.
Y en Windows es muy similar.
As long as you've got PIP installed and Python installed
Siempre que tengas instalado pip y Python
and your scripts are correct, you
y tus scripts sean correctos,
should be able to do this in pretty much the same way.
deberías ser capaz de hacer esto de forma muy similar.